Guide to the Otto Rank Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Otto Rank Papers,
1903-1988
1903-1940.
Rank, Otto, 1884-1939.
18 linear ft. (ca. 2,650 items in 40 boxes and 1 flat box).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079582
Biographical Note
Psychotherapist and one-time associate of Sigmund Freud.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of: (1) A group of early materials written between 1903-1905, before Rank met Freud. This includes 4 daybooks, a notebook of dreams, a notebook of poems, the manuscripts of "Der Kunstler;" (2) Correspondence between Freud and Rank between 1906-1924, including the controversy over The Trauma Of Birth. 40 a.l.s. from Freud and typed copies from Rank, with a few letters to and from Ferenczi; (3) Copies and some originals of the circular letters by members of the inner circle, Ernest Jones, Abraham, Eitingon, Ferenczi, Rank and Freud, 1920-1924; (4) Original handwritten manuscripts, typed copies, notes and corrections of Rank's major works; (5) Rank's own listing and comments on his writings and publications (to 1930); (6) Rank's published works--20 titles.
Mrs. Simon, formerly the wife of Otto Rank, presented a group of manuscripts by and about him including the introduction and part of the text of his last book Beyond Psychology.
The original manuscript of Freud's Massenpsychologie und Ich-Aanalyse with the published English translation by James Strachey; and two other Freud manuscripts..
Helene Rank Velfort, his daughter, has presented a group of books from his library which contain many revisions and annotations.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Cataloged Documents
Series IV: Arranged Manuscripts
Series V: Arranged Photographs and Drawings
Series VI: Printed Series
Series VII: Miscellaneous
Series VIII: Gifts
Subjects
Abraham, Karl, 1877-1925.; Eitingon, M. (Max), 1880-1943.; Ferenczi, Sándor, 1873-1933.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939.; Jones, Ernest, 1879-1958.; Strachey, James.; Mental health.; Psychoanalysis.; Psychotherapy.; Announcements.; Applications.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Brochures.; Charts.; Clippings.; Daybooks.; Diplomas.; Dissertations.; Drawings.; Galley proofs.; Illustrations.; Inventories.; Journals.; Lectures.; Lists.; Manuscripts for publication.; Minutes.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Obituaries.; Outlines.; Photographs.; Photoprints.; Poems.; Programs.; Proofs.; Reports.; Reviews.; Speeches.; Tickets.; Psychoanalysts.; Psychotherapists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Papers Taft, Dr.Jessie and Mrs. Pierre Simon; Otto Rank Assoc. Gift
12/--/1989 M-89-12--- Annotated books Velfort, Helene Rank Gift
1990 M-1990 Annotated books Simon, Estelle Gift
12/26/1990 M-90-12-26 Papers Lieberman, E.J. Gift
12/22/1991 M-91-12-22 Books Novey, Riva Gift
M-12-26-94 4 books re Otto Rank Lieberman, James Gift
Alternate Formats
Rundbriefe (Boxes Ib, IIa, IIb, IIc); General correspondence (Box Ia); "Lohengrin Sage," "Incest Motif," "Art and Artist," and "Genetic Psychology" are on microfilm.
Gift of Dr Jessie Taft and Mrs Pierre Simon, 1957.
Gift of the Otto Rank Association, 1984, 1985, and 1986.
Gift of Helene Rank Velfort, 1989.
Gift of Estelle Buel Rank Simon, 1990.
Gift of E. James Lieberman, 1990 & 1994.
Gift of Riva Novey, 1991.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Subseries I.1: Freud-Rank Correspondence, 1907-1925
    Originally in three envelopes, the Freud-Rank Ferenczi Committee letters are in a physical order determined by Rank and must be retained in this original order; therefore, the folder numbers are out of sequence with this alphabetic listing. Box 1 contains folders 1-82.
    - Abraham, Karl et al. To Otto Rank, Berlin, 25 Dec. 1924, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - &reas, Lou To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 13 July 1922, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 19)
      [includes note signed by Anna Freud]
    - Bernays, Edward L. To Otto Rank, New York, 19 May 1924, (1 page t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 78)
      [copy]
    - Eitingon, Max To Otto Rank, Berlin, 26 Dec. 1924, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Eitingon, Max et al. To Otto Rank, Berlin, 25 Dec. 1924, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Ferenczi, S&or To Otto Rank, Budapest, 18 March - 7 June 1924, (4 a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 41, 48, 52, 53)
    - Freud, Anna To Otto Rank, Gotingen, 31 July 1922, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Committee, Vienna, 26 Nov. 1922 Jan. 1924, (1 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 38, 69)
    - Sigmund Freud To Sandor Ferenczi, Vienna, 20 - 26 March 1924, (2 t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 42, 47)
      [Copies]
    - Sigmund Freud To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 1907 - 1925, (37 a.l.s., 3 a.n.s., 4 t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 20, 21, 22, 23, 25, 26, 27, 28, 30, 31, 35, 36, 37, 40, 45, 50, 51, 54, 56, 57, 64, 68, 71, 72, 75, 76, 79, 80, 81.)
    - Jones, Ernest To Committee, Elsted, England, Aug 1922, (3 page t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Jones, Ernest To Otto Rank, London, 1 Jan 1925, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Rank, Otto To Committee, Vienna, 1920 - 1925, (4 t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 13, 59, 63, 70)
      [(carbons)]
    - Rank, Otto To Sigmund Freud, Vienna and New York, 1923 - 1924, (2 a.l.s., 1 a.l., 3 t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 39, 44, 46, 55, 73, 74)
    - Rank, Otto To Sandor Ferenczi, Vienna and New York, 20 March - 10 Dec. 1924, (3 t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 43, 49, 58)
    - Rank, Otto To Edward L. Bernays, New York, 17 May 1924, (1 page t.l.) (Box 1, Folder 77)
      [(copy)]
    - Sachs, Hans et al. To Otto Rank, Berlin, 25 Dec. 1924, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Subseries I.2: Rundbriefe
    Letters regarding the debate over "Das Trauma der Geburt" and other psychoanalytic issues
    - Abraham, Karl To Committee, Berlin, 1920 - 1923, (19 t.l.s., 5 t.l.s. (carbon), 1 p.c.s.) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 88, 90, 104, 108, 110, 113, 116, 121, 125, 128, 132, 134, 138, 142, 146, 150, 150, 154, 158, 178, 182, 187, 189, 197, 325, 374.)
    - Abraham, Karl & Max Eitingon To Committee, Berlin, 1920 - 1923, (7 t.l.s., 2 t.l. (carbon)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 119, 212, 216, 218, 258, 262, 266, 361, 375)
    - Abraham, Karl et al. To Committee, Berlin, 1920 - 1923, (23 t.l.s., 1 t.l.s. (carbon)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 193, 205, 222, 252, 283, 297, 306, 312, 314, 319, 329, 334, 347, 351, 366, 368, 371, 384, 392, 397, 401, 404, 406.)
    - Abraham, Karl To Committee, Berlin, 1921-1924, (22 t.l.s., 1 t.l.s. (carbon)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 115, 174, 201, 209, 227, 229, 236, 240, 247, 248, 269, 273, 277, 288, 293, 398, 337, 340, 345, 354, 358, 364, 380.)
    - Eitingon, Max To Committee, [n.p.] & Berlin, 1921 - 1923, (1 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s.) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 168, 304, 379)
    - Ferenczi, S&or To Committee, Budapest, 1920 - 1924, (1 a.l., 10 a.l.s., 44 a.l. (carbon), 5 p.c.s., 7 t.l.s., 2 t.l.s. (carbon)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 86, 91, 94, 98, 102, 106, 117, 123, 127, 130, 136, 139, 143, 149, 151, 155, 161, 163, 170, 171, 175, 180, 183, 188, 190, 194, 200, 202, 208, 211, 219, 228, 230, 233, 237, 241, 244, 251, 256, 260, 263, 267, 270, 274, 279, 281, 289, 292, 294, 308, 309, 311, 315, 321, 326, 333, 338, 343, 348, 350, 355, 359, 369, 373, 385, 388, 393, 395, 403, 408)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Committee, Vienna, [n.d.] & 1921 - 1922, (2 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 1 folder (7 pages of holograph, 1 page signed)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 84, 147, 167, 285, 323)
    - Jones, Ernest To Committee, London, 1920 - 1924, (81 t.l.s., 1 t.l.s. (carbon)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 89, 92, 95, 99, 103, 107, 111, 112, 120, 129, 131, 135, 140, 144, 148, 152, 156, 159, 164, 169, 172, 176, 181, 184, 186, 191, 195, 198, 203, 306, 213, 215, 220, 223, 225, 231, 235, 238, 242, 245, 249, 253, 255, 259, 264, 268, 272, 275, 280, 282, 286, 290, 295, 300, 303, 305, 310, 317, 320, 322, 328, 331, 335, 339, 344, 346, 353, 356, 362, 365, 370, 376, 378, 381, 383, 391, 396, 398, 400, 405, 407)
    - Mackenzie, W To Committee, Genoa, 23 Oct. 1920, (3 page t.l.) (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Pfister, O To Committee, Zurich, 26 Oct 1920, (2 page t.l.) (Box 2, Folder 100)
    - Rank, Otto To Sigmund Freud, Vienna, 22 April 1922, (1 page t.l.) (Box 3, Folder 277a)
      [(carbon copy of page two only) (filed as #277a of the Rundbriefe)]
    - Rank, Otto To Committee, Vienna & Seefeld, 1920 - 1924, (1 t.l (carbon), 5 t.l., 5 t.l.s. (carbons), 65 t.l. (carbons)) (Box 2 & 3, Folder 87, 93, 96, 101, 105, 109, 114, 118, 122, 126, 133, 137, 141, 145, 153, 157, 160, 165, 166, 173, 177, 179, 185, 192, 196, 199, 204, 207, 210, 214, 247, 221, 224, 226, 232, 239, 243, 246, 250, 254, 257, 261, 265, 271, 276, 278, 284, 287, 291, 296, 399, 301, 302, 307, 313, 316, 324, 330, 332, 336, 341, 342, 349, 352, 357, 360, 363, 367, 372, 377, 382, 387, 390, 394, 399, 402.)
    - Sachs, Hans To Committee, Berlin, 16 Jan. 1924, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 3, Folder 389)
      [(on verso t.l.s. from Eitingon)]
    - Sachs, Hans To Committee, Berlin, 1 April 1920 & 2 March 1921, (1 a.l.s., 1 a.l.s. (carbon)) (Box 2, Folder 85, 162)
  - Subseries I.3: Journal Correspondence
    Letters regarding journal printed in Vienna. In Box 4, Folders 411-555
    - Clark, L. Pierce To Ernest Jones, New York, 10 Nov. 1920, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 4, Folder 535)
    - Forsyth, David To Ernest Jones, London, 18 April 1920, (1 t.l. (copy)) (Box 4, Folder 443)
      [(filed with Ernest Jones- folder 443)]
    - Forsyth, David To Ernest Jones, London, 21 April 1920, (1 page t.l. (copy)) (Box 4, Folder 448)
      [(filed with Ernest Jones folder 448)]
    - Hiller, Eric To Otto Rank, London, 8 Jan. - 6 Dec. 1920, (1 a.l.s., 1 p.c.s., 2 p.c., 42 t.l.s.) (Box 4, Folder 412, 413, 415, 419, 421, 424, 426, 427, 432, 434, 435, 436, 438, 444, 446, 447, 449, 453, 458, 461, 463, 479, 480, 484, 488, 494, 496, 502, 504, 505, 506, 507, 508, 509, 510, 513, 517, 522, 526, 527, 531, 534, 540, 541, 547, 554.)
    - Jones, Ernest To Otto Rank, London & Elsted, 20 Jan. - 14 Dec. 1920, (1 a.l.s., 1 a.n.s., 27 t.l.s., 6 t.l., 8 p.c., 1 telegram) (Box 4, Folder 414, 417, 418, 425, 429, 433, 437, 439, 450, 454, 455, 456, 457, 462, 465, 466, 469, 470, 472, 473, 476, 478, 483, 486, 490, 493, 497, 503, 512, 516, 518, 519, 520, 521, 528, 532, 537, 538, 539, 542, 545, 546, 551, 555.)
    - Jones, Ernest To David Forsyth, London, 20 April 1920, (1 page t.l. (copy)) (Box 4, Folder 443)
    - Jones, Ernest To David Forsyth, London, 24 April 1920, (4 page t.l.s. (carbon copy)) (Box 4, Folder 448)
    - Rank, Otto To Hans Liebermann, Vienna, 30 Sept. 1920, (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 4, Folder 511)
    - Rank, Otto To Katherine Jokl Jones (Mrs. Ernest), Vienna, 30 July 1920, (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 4, Folder 491)
    - Rank, Otto To Ernest Jones, Vienna, 16 Feb. - 4 Dec. 1920, (1 t.l., 30 t.l. (carbon)) (Box 4, Folder 420, 423, 430, 442, 445, 452, 459, 460, 464, 468, 471, 474, 477, 481, 487, 489, 495, 498, 499, 501, 515, 523, 524, 530, 533, 536, 544, 548, 550, 552, 553.)
    - Rank, Otto To Eric Hiller, Vienna, 29 Jan. - 30 Nov. 1920, (1 t.l., 2 t.l. (copies), 14 t.l. (carbon)) (Box 4, Folder 416, 422, 428, 431, 440, 441, 451, 475, 482, 485, 492, 500, 514, 525, 529, 543, 549.)
    - Smith, Ely Jellife To Otto Rank, New York, 6 June 1920, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 4, Folder 467)
  - Subseries I.4: General Correspondence
    - Arnold, [?] Postal to Rank. Homer., [n.p.], 29 January 1918, (1 p.c.s.) (Box 5)
    - Luria, Al. To Otto Rank, Wien, 25 September 1923, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Beck To Otto Rank, Wien, 14 November 1917, (3 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Brill, Abraham To Otto Rank, New York, 28 Sept. 1920, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [With unrelated newsclipping]
    - Brink, Louise To Otto Rank. Der Doppelganger, New York, 4 June 1920, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Buerki, Emil To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 19 September 1923, (1 p.c.) (Box 5)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd. To Stanley Unwin, London, 2 Jan. 1922, (2 page t.l.) (Box 5)
      [(copy signed by L.E. Poilinger. Filed with Ernest Jones correspondence to Stanley Unwin 5 Jan 1922.)]
    - Coriat, Isador H. To Ernest Jones, Boston, 4 April 1921, (4 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Danoli, L. To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 10 May 1908, (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Doerpfeld, Wilhelm To [Otto Rank], Berlin, 1 Feb. 1919, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Drerup, E To Otto Rank. Homer., [n.p.], 1914, (1 p.c.s.) (Box 5)
    - Ferenczi, S&or To Otto Rank, [n.p.], [1924], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [(with English translation)]
    - Ferenczi, S&or To [Otto Rank?], [n.p.], 20 June 1913, (4 page a.l.) (Box 5)
    - Flammarion Library To Otto Rank. Kunst und Kunstler., [n.p.], 20 September 1933, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Floch, J. To Otto Rank, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Forsyth, David To Ernest Jones, [n.p.], 11 Feb. 1922, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [(Filed with Ernest Jones 6 Feb 1922)]
    - Freud, Ernst To Otto Rank, Berlin, 26 October 1922, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Freud, Ernst To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 15 November 1922, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Committee, [n.p.], [19--], (3 a.l.) (Box 5)
      [(Includes summary of contents in English)]
    - Freud, Sigmund To Otto Rank, Karlsbad & Vienna, 1907 - 1913, (3 a.p.c.s., 2 a.l.s. (on cards)) (Box 5)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Committee, [n.p.], [n.d.], (8 page a.l.) (Box 5)
      [Draft; includes typescript summary of contents in English, 2 copies]
    - Freud, Sigmund To Committee, [n.p.], [n.d.], (4 page a.l.) (Box 5)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 25 July 1913 - September 1922, (4 a.p.c.s.) (Box 5)
    - Freud, Sigmund To Edward Bernays, Vienna, April 7 & June 20, 1924, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [6459B 9/28/99 Accn: 99/00-23]
    - Gotz, Berndt Letters to Otto Rank, [n.p.], 8 July and 16 July 1931, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Grotjahn, Martin To [?], Beverly Hills, CA, 29 Feb 1968 (Box 5)
      [Includes translations, photocopies, and photos of letters dated 16 July 1916 and 26 July 1916 from Freud to Rank.]
    - Halle, S. To Dr. Gelliffe, [n.p.], [n.d.], (5 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Heusler, &reas To Otto Rank, Berlin, 2 Feb. 1919, (2 page t.p.c.s.) (Box 5)
    - E.J. Letter to Rank. Doppelganger., [n.p.], 7 July 1920 [?], (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Jacobs, D.K. To Otto Rank. Kunst und Kunstler, New York, 24 March 1932, (1 page 1 t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Jones, Ernest To David Forsyth, [n.p.], 6 Feb 1922, (1 page t.l.s. (carbon copy initialed by Jones)) (Box 5)
    - Jones, Ernest To Stanley Unwin, [London?], 5 Jan 1922, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [(carbon copy initialed by Jones)]
    - Jones, Ernest To Otto Rank, London & Elsted, 1919 - [1923?], (2 t.l.s., 1 t.p.c.) (Box 5)
    - Kaspar [Franz Deuticke Bookstore] To Otto Rank. Books about Mark Twain, [n.p.], 18 September 1933, (1 p.c.) (Box 5)
    - Kerr, A. To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 4 July 1913, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Koonerg, Karl To Otto Rank. Traumdeutung., [n.p.], 3 May 1909, (1 page t.l.) (Box 5)
    - Mei To Otto Rank, [n.p.], [n.d.], (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Mellert, K. To Otto Rank. Odipustraum., [n.p.], 6 September 1923, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Merrill, Greta To Otto Rank., New York, 24 October 1935, (2 page a.l. & t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Mielle, F. van To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 29 September 1925, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Odier, Charles To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 22 January 1926, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Peter Davies Ltd To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 21 October 1933, (1 page t.l.) (Box 5)
      [Re: Publishing of "Charles Dickens"]
    - Pohek, Margueritte To [?], [n.p.], [n.d.], (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [Includes her transcription of an Isidor Sax lettter]
    - Rank, Otto To J. Jessie Taft, New York, 16 Oct. 1939, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Ethel Seiderman Wannemacher, Buffalo & New York, 1936 - 1938, (2 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Dorothy Hankins, New York & Philadelphia, 1934 - 1939, (8 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s., 1 telegram) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Harry Bone, New York & Paris, 1934 - 1935, (2 t.l.s., 2 a.l.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Pearce Bailey, [v.p.], 1933 - 1939, (15 t.l.s., 1 t.l., 6 a.l.s., 1 telegram) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Lloyd J. Thompson, Paris, 18 March 1929, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Virginia P. Robinson, [v.p.], 1927 - 1939, (9 a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [With 8 related items]
    - Rank, Otto To Virginia Robinson, [Philadephia], 1 Nov. & 1 Dec. 1927, (2 a.d.s.) (Box 5)
      [(receipts to Virginia Robinson for payments for her psychoanalytic sessions with Rank. Filed with 9 a.l.s. to Virginia Robinson 1927 - 1939)]
    - Rank, Otto To J. Jessie Taft, [v.p.], 1924 - 1939, (195 a.l.s., 1 a.n., 1 a.p.c.s., 10 t.l.s., 1 t.l., 1 telegram) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To George Wilbur, New York & Paris, 1927 - 1934, (4 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Theodor Reik, Vienna, 14 Nov. 1922, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - [Rank, Otto] To Karl Abraham, Modling, 8 Aug 1921, (2 page t.l.) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Deutsche Bank, Filale Munchen, [Vienna], 23 Oct. & 2 Nov. 1920, (2 t.l. (carbons)) (Box 5)
      [(2 replies from bank enclosed)]
    - Rank, Otto To Abraham A. Brill, [Vienna], 1920 - 1921, (3 t.l. (carbons)) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Ernest Jones, [Vienna], 11 Jan 1919, (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Varendonck, J., [n.p.], 14 December 1923, (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To L. Brink. Der Doppelganger., [n.p.], 1 July 1920, (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 5)
    - Rank, Otto To Beatrice Taussig, [n.p.], Aug. 7 & Aug. 18 1933, (1 page each. t.l. (carbon)) (Box 5)
      [About Mark Twain]
    - Reik, Theodor To Otto Rank. Inzest-Motiv, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [Includes his mss. "Der Traum von Geschlechts verkehr mit der Mütter"]
    - Ressman To Otto Rank. Der Mythus, [n.p.], 28 April 1909, (3 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Robenus Letter to Rank, [n.p.], 14 September 1912, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Rosenbaum, Belle To Otto Rank. Das Trauma., [n.p.], 8 March 1930, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Sax, Isidor To [Marguerite Pohek], [n.p.], 10 January 1940, (4 page t.l. ) (Box 5)
      [Letter transcribed by M. Pohek. This is filed in the M. Pohek folder above.]
    - Schultz, W. To Otto Rank. Psych. Beitrage., [n.p.], 11 November 1919, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [O.R.A. gift 1984]
    - Schuetterheim, W.F. Letter to Otto Rank. Homer., [n.p.], 9 January 1923, (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
      [ORA gift 1984]
    - Taft Warner, Lorraine To Jessie Taft, [n.p.], February 1935, (6 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Taussig, Beatrice To George Wilbur, [n.p.], 19 December 1934, (3 page t.l.) (Box 5)
    - Taussig, Beatrice To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 7 May 1935, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Teller, V. To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 9 March 1923, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Tridon, &re To [?], New York, [n.d.], (1 page t.l. (carbon)) (Box 5)
    - Tsecker, Annalia To Otto Rank, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Tubjanski, M. To Otto Rank, Leningrad, 8 & 10 March 1925, (2 a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Varendock, J. To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 6 January 1924, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Vorwahl, Henner To Otto Rank, Elze, Germany, 12 April 1924, (1 a.p.c.s.) (Box 5)
    - Vorwahl, Henner To Otto Rank, [n.p.], [n.d.], (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Wessel, Rosa To Otto Rank, [n.p.], 14 June 19[?], (4 page a.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Wilbur, George To Otto Rank, South Dennis, MA, 12 July 1932, (2 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
    - Wilbur, George To Beatrice Taussig, [n.p.], 5 May 1935, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 5)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  Manuscripts by authors other than Rank.
  - Abraham, Karl Obituary of Dr Rudolph Foerster, (2 pages) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Abrahamson, J. Multiple Sklerose bei Mutter und Sohn, (3 pp Manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    [Copied by Rank]
  - Bailey, Pearce An Introduction to Rankian Psychology, Psychological Center, Paris, [n.d.], (44 pp Annotated typescript) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    [ ]
  - Bailey, Pearce An Introduction to the Psychology of Dr. Rank, Paris, 1935, (38 t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Berger, A.F. Warheit und Irrtum, Leipzig, 1897, (4 page Manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    [Aristoteles' Katharsis Theory. Copied by Rank]
  - Burton, Robert The Anatomy of Melancholy, (3 pp pages) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Freud, Sigmund Ein Fall von Fussfetichismus., Vienna, March 11, 1914, (3 page Typescript) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    [Minutes of the meeting of the 21st session of the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society]
  - Freud, Sigmund Erfahrungen und Beispiele der analyticshen Praktik, (2 pages) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Freud, Sigmund [Ergaenzungen zur Traumlehre], (4 page Manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 9)
    [Includes typescript summary of contents in English]
  - Freud, Sigmund Homer, [n.p.], 1908-1909, (2 page a.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    [See Manuscript Flat Box 174]
  - Freud, Sigmund Nibelungen, Vienna, 1909, (2 page Photocopy) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    [Notes on the Ring of the Nibelungs. 1985 Gift]
  - Freud, Sigmund Nibelungenlied in Homer., [n.p.], 21 Feb. 1909, (1 page a.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - [?] Psychoanalytische Situation in Polen, (2 pp pages) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - [?] Schweiz, (3 pp a.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Reich, Wilhelm Die Taetigkeit der Zentrallstelle [fuer psychoanalytische Literatur...], [n.p.], [192?], (6pp Annotated typescript) (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Freud, Sigmund Das Trauma der Geburt, [n.p.], [1924], (5pp pages) (Box 6, Folder 16)
    [Critique of Rank's "Das Trauma der Geburt." Not complete. It might be part of one of the Rundbriefe]
  - Freud, Sigmund Traumdeutung, [n.p.], [1913-1914], (7 pp Page proofs) (Box 6, Folder 17)
    [Note written by Freud acknowledging the collaboration of Rank. With proofs of title page and 4 preliminary pages.]
  - Freud, Sigmund Traumdeutung, [n.p.], 1914, (11 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Freud, Sigmund 3 Zeiten, [n.p.] & St. Annes, 1 & 8 September 1908, (4 pages) (Box 6, Folder 19)
    [Notes on Otto Rank's "Homer." Taken from folder labeled der "Homer plan" ORA Gift 1984]
  - Freud, Sigmund 3 Zeiten, St. Annes, 1908-1909, (7 pages) (Box 6, Folder 20)
    [Notes on Rank's "Homer" and other authors. With notes added in several hands. Taken from folder labeled "Homer plan." ORA gift 1984]
  - Freud, Sigmund Zur Genese des Fetichismus. Vienna, February 17, 1909, (17 pages) (Box 6, Folder 21)
    [Minutes of the meeting of the Vienna Psychoanalytic Society written in the hand of Otto Rank Includes photocopy of published version.]
  - Gotz, Berndt Das Bild des Todes, [n.p.], 1931, (4 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Gotz, Berndt Das Hawdalah Ritual, [n.p.], May 1931, (1 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Gotz, Berndt Das studentische Ritual, [n.p.], 1930, (6 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Gotz, Berndt Das Zweigeschlechterwesen, [n.p.], [1930], (10 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Harodecki, S Der juedische Mythos, Berlin, [n.d.], (2 pages) (Box 6, Folder 26)
    [Written in the hand of Otto Rank]
  - Hollos, Istvan Die Psychoneurose eines Fruhgelborenen, (6 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Juer, F. & Marbach, O. Eine nudslaurische Marchenparallele, [n.p.], [n.d.], (32 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Klette, Werner Das Experiment des Dr. Forgues, (3 pages) (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Krieger, Herbert. Some aspects of northwest coast indian art. Pamphlet., [n.p.], [n.d.], (12 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - L&auer, Karl Passive Technik, (3 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Lieberman, E. J. The Rank-Wilbur Correspondence, [n.p.], 1979, (17 page t.ms.) (Box 6, Folder 31a)
    [From Journal 14 (1) of O.R.A.]
  - Maturis, E. [There is however...], [n.p.], [1930], (12 pp Manuscript & typed manuscript) (Box 6, Folder 32)
    [Evaluation of Rank's work. With a note from Virginia Robinson]